Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, daf דף daf is lamed bet
למד ב, lamed bet, and we pick up at the very bottom,
two lines from the bottom, and the
so again two lines from the bottom on lamed aleph למד א
lamed aleph amud bet עמוד ב. amud bet. Amar Rav Yehiel אמר
רב יחיאל Amar Rav Yehiel and the issue had been the question
about can you trust that a shaliach oseh shelichuto שליח עושה שליחותו
shaliach oseh shelichuto because thank you, the Mishnah משנה Mishnah said that
you can send an eruv עירוב eruv through a cheresh shoteh ve-katan
חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve-katan who themselves cannot place an eruv
עירוב, eruv, but you can send it to somebody who will get
receive it from them and that person will put it down. So
the Gemara גמרא Gemara had two questions. The first question is how
do you know that they've delivered it? And there it says since
it's a cheresh shoteh ve-katan חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh ve-katan, so
people that were concerned about their level of intellect or their level
of responsibility and so on, you actually have to observe it being
delivered. You cannot assume that it was done. But then the next
question is, okay, but even when the adult receives it, how do
you know that he did what he said he would do? How
do you know he actually went and put it down? And there
the answer was hazakah shaliach oseh shelichuto חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו. hazakah
shaliach oseh shelichuto. You can assume that if somebody has agreed to
do something for you he will take care of it. And now
the Gemara גמרא Gemara enters into that question whether we really make
that assumption. So again, two lines from the bottom. Amar Rav Yehiel
אמר רב יחיאל Amar Rav Yehiel says Rav Yehiel, hazakah shaliach oseh
shelichuto חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו. hazakah shaliach oseh shelichuto. So that was
the end of yesterday's discussion about why we can assume this person
in the end did what he said he would do. Amar Rav
Nachman אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, so now Rav Nachman says
here's the halachah הלכה. halachah. Beshel Torah בשל תורה beshel Torah when
you're dealing with biblical matters, ein hazakah shaliach oseh shelichuto אין חזקה
שליח עושה שליחותו. ein hazakah shaliach oseh shelichuto. You cannot rely on
that assumption. Sometimes people are lazy or negligent or sometimes things come
up even with their best intentions. So our case is a rabbinic,
allowing you to walk outside of the techum תחום. techum. So for
rabbinic purposes you can assume somebody said they would do something, they
took care of it. But for biblical purposes you cannot. Beshel sofrim
בשל סופרים beshel sofrim so when it's rabbinic, hazakah חזקה hazakah top
of lamed bet למד ב lamed bet amud aleph עמוד א, amud
aleph, hazakah shaliach oseh shelichuto חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו hazakah shaliach oseh
shelichuto you can you can have that assumption, you can that the
shaliach שליח shaliach did what he said he would do. Rav Sheshet
רב ששת Rav Sheshet amar Rav Sheshet אמר רב ששת amar Rav
Sheshet is even more lenient, he said echad zeh ve-echad zeh אחד
זה ואחד זה echad zeh ve-echad zeh whether biblical or rabbinic, hazakah
shaliach oseh shelichuto חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו hazakah shaliach oseh shelichuto you
can assume for halachic purposes if somebody said they would do it,
they'll do it. It doesn't mean it happens one hundred percent of
the time, but that is a good enough rule that of that
you can assume that for purposes even for biblical issues. Yes.
So what is Rav Yehiel רב יחיאל Rav Yehiel say? He's is
he the same?
No, Rav Yehiel רב יחיאל Rav Yehiel was really the end of
yesterday's discussion. He was explaining how the Mishnah משנה Mishnah makes sense.
Our Mishnah משנה Mishnah makes sense because you can assume the shaliach
שליח shaliach will do what he said. And then the Gemara גמרא
Gemara turned, right, that was a that was a gloss on the
Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. And then Rav Nachman רב נחמן Rav Nachman and
Rav Sheshet רב ששת Rav Sheshet are talking about the actual halachah
הלכה. halachah. So Rav Nachman רב נחמן Rav Nachman distinguishes between biblical
and rabbinic and Rav Sheshet רב ששת Rav Sheshet does not. So
now they're just moving into halachic statements, not explaining the Mishnah משנה.
Mishnah. Okay, so now the Gemara גמרא Gemara is going to to
see if we can prove one way or the other whether this
works by biblical issues. Amar Rav Sheshet אמר רב ששת Amar Rav
Sheshet says Rav Sheshet, mina amina lah מנא אמינא לה mina amina
lah where do I get this idea from that it applies even
in in biblical cases? Detnan דתנן detnan we taught in the Mishnah
משנה Mishnah very appropriate for this time of year, mishekarev ha-omer משקרב
העומר mishekarev ha-omer when the omer עומר omer was brought on the
second day of Pesach פסח, Pesach, hutzar ha-chadash miyad הותר החדש מיד.
hutzar ha-chadash miyad. The new grain was immediately permissible. Whenever the ha-chadash
החדש ha-chadash the omer עומר omer was brought, if it was brought
at nine AM, you could eat the new grain at nine AM.
Ve-harachokim והרחוקים ve-harachokim how about people that were distant from the Beit
HaMikdash בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and did not know exactly what time
of day it was brought? So mutarim mechatzot hayom va'eilach מותרים מחצות
היום ואילך. mutarim mechatzot hayom va'eilach.
They're permissible from noon onward. So they can assume that it was
brought by noon. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says ve-hachadash d'oraisa hu
והחדש דאורייתא הוא ve-hachadash d'oraisa hu that's a biblical prohibition, chadash חדש,
chadash, u-ktani harachokim mutarim mechatzot hayom va'eilach וקתני הרחוקים מותרים מחצות היום
ואילך u-ktani harachokim mutarim mechatzot hayom va'eilach
and you see that they can assume that the that it will
get taken care of by chatzot חצות. chatzot. Now, the interesting question
here is throughout which is that, you know, okay
maybe I can assume the guy will do it, but in what
timeframe? Right? So now if there's a necessary timeframe like he has
to do it before Shabbos שבת, Shabbos, so maybe I can assume
he did it before Shabbos שבת. Shabbos. But to what degree you
know, what is the timeframe in which you're if we're saying we
can assume he did it, that you assume he did it in?
So here, the you know, here the idea is that somehow we
have to assume that there was a people were working with the
assumption it would be done by chatzot חצות, chatzot, and therefore since
the Kohanim כהנים Kohanim knew that, they would make sure to bring
it by chatzot חצות. chatzot. That's sort of how Tosafot תוספות Tosafot
explains explains what's going on, or else you know why we don't
normally say hazakah shaliach oseh shelichuto חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו hazakah shaliach
oseh shelichuto by chatzot חצות, chatzot, right? But here, that was somehow
seen as the as the time to get it done by, and
therefore people could work with that assumption.
Well that's what the Gemara גמרא's Gemara answer is going to be,
right? First of all, they've got a mitzvah מצוה mitzvah to do
it, second of all they're public officials. So as far as the
mitzvah מצוה mitzvah Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says yeah, but the mitzvah מצוה
mitzvah wouldn't have required them to do it by chatzot חצות. chatzot.
Okay, so let's see what the anyway the answer is. Rav Nachman
רב נחמן Rav Nachman and Rav Nachman רב נחמן Rav Nachman say
back exactly what Tosafot תוספות Tosafot said, so hasam kedekatani ta'ama התם
כדיקתני טעמא hasam kedekatani ta'ama there
it's because the reason is given in the Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, lefi
sheyodim she'ein Beit Din mitatzlin bo לפי שיודעים שאין בית דין מתעצלים
בו lefi sheyodim she'ein Beit Din mitatzlin bo because people can know
that Beit Din בית דין Beit Din won't be lazy about it.
So meaning Beit Din בית דין Beit Din takes pains to make
sure it gets done by chatzot חצות. chatzot. It's interesting in general
how חז״ל Chazal see that there was a בית דין beis din
that supervised כהנים, kohanim, you know, the whole sort of intersection of
rabbinic and temple-based authority and so on. Anyway, but he says there
they were particularly on top of them to make sure it got
done, that you can't make that assumption by a normal individual. ואיכא
דאמרי, V'ik'a d'amri, some say, אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav Nachman that
actually רב נחמן Rav Nachman used that to prove his side. מנא
מנא לן, Mina minalah, how do I know for biblical purposes you
cannot rely on it? דקתני טעמא Dik'tani ta'ama because the only reason
for the עומר Omer that you can assume by חצות chatzos is
because it says לפי שיודעין שאין בית דין מתעצלין בו, l'fi sheyodin
she'ein beis din misatzlin bo, that we know בית דין beis din
will not be lazy about it. בית דין הוא דלא מתעצלין בו,
Beis din hu d'lo misatzlin bo, so בית דין beis din is
a unique situation, it's because בית דין beis din is taking care
of it we know it'll get done. הא שליח, Ha shaliach, if
it was a normal individual that you told to do something for
you, מתעצל בו, misatzel bo, then you would have to be concerned
that they would be lazy and wouldn't get it done. So that
seems like it really is only because of that reason, it's not
a general rule. Because you could also say same thing by saying
כהנים זריזים הם.
kohanim zerizim hein.
Right, exactly, so it is interesting again this is based on the
משנה, Mishnah, but yes, it could have just made it about כהנים
kohanim and it does introduce the בית דין beis din aspect. So
how does רב ששת Rav Sheshet answer this? Why does this sound
like it's only because of בית דין? beis din? רב ששת אמר
לך, Rav Sheshet amar lach, בית דין אל פלגא
דיומא, beis din al palga d'yoma, like we said before, because of
the בית דין, beis din, therefore you can assume it gets done
by noon. שליח, Shaliach, if however it was just a normal messenger,
you could still assume he would do it, but כולי יומא, kulei
yoma, he'd do it sometime later in the day. Again, the question
always has to do like what is your assumed time frame? עומר
Omer has to be brought by the end of the day. עירוב
תחומין Eruv techumin has to be put down before the end of
the day. If you make a שליח shaliach to deliver a גט,
get, right? So you know maybe they have to get on a
plane and it's a three days journey and it's not necessarily the
same time frame. But within this context, he's saying you can assume
they'll do it within the day. To do it earlier than that
time frame, that was only because of בית דין. beis din. Okay,
so now רב ששת Rav Sheshet is going to try again. אמר
רב ששת מנא מנא לן, Amar Rav Sheshet mina minalah,
where do I get this from? דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in the
ברייתא Braisa again that it works even for biblical, האשה שיולדה או
זיבה, haishah sheyeledah o zivah, if a woman has just given birth
or she was a זבה, zavah, and in order to eat קרבנות,
korbanos, it's not only enough to wait the amount of days, you
know, seven days or it's fourteen days or whatever the case might
be, but she has to bring a קרבן korban and go to
the מקוה, mikvah, but she has to bring a קרבן korban at
the end if she wants to be fully טהור tahor to eat
קרבנות. korbanos. So what would a woman do? מביאה מעות, Mavia maos,
she would take the money for the birds which would be the
קרבן, korban, ונתנה בשופר, v'nosna b'shofar, she'd put it in the box,
it'd be a box in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash for these
קרבנות, korbanos, and she wouldn't have to, and she just like a
פושקא, pushka, she'd put however the amount of money is, she wouldn't
have to go buy the birds, she wouldn't have to wait till
she saw the כהנים kohanim bring it. She comes in the morning,
she puts the money in the
פושקא, pushka, וטובלת ואוכלת בקדשים לערב, v'tovela v'ocheles b'kodshim l'erev, and by
nighttime she can already eat קרבנות korbanos because she can assume that
the כהנים kohanim will
use all the money to, for this was a box set aside
for money for bird קרבן korban for women, you know, who would
bring it for לידה leida and זיבה ziva purposes. And therefore what
they would make sure is that each day they would constantly be
emptying the box and using it to buy birds and bring the
birds those days. And therefore she can assume it gets done. Sometimes
the box is lining? Yeah, they had different boxes, they had thirteen
different boxes for different
purposes. Yeah, so the גמרא Gemara says מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, so
what is the reason she can assume it'll get done? לאו משום
דאמרינן חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו, Lav mishum d'amrinan hazakah shaliach oseh shlichuso,
you assume the agent does what he's been, you know, what his
agency. And again, this by the way ties in as רש״י Rashi
mentions to a classic idea that כהנים kohanim are שלוחי דידן. shluchei
didan. You know, there's a question in the גמרא, Gemara, do כהנים,
kohanim, are they doing God's work or our work? Or obviously the
answer's a little bit of both. But anyway, they're there to bring
our קרבנות, korbanos, so there's an implicit שליחות shlichus and you can
assume that they have taken care of it, so you see that's
the rule. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman and רב נחמן Rav Nachman
will say back, similar to the previous answer, התם כדרב שמיה, Hasam
k'd'Rav Shmaya, that's a special case like where שמיה Shmaya says. דאמר
רב שמיה חזקה אין בית דין של כהנים, D'amar Rav Shmaya hazakah
ein beis din shel kohanim, here it identifies it as the בית
דין beis din of כהנים, kohanim, but still sort of seeing בית
דין beis din as the authority, we can make assumption that the
בית דין beis din of the כהנים kohanim עומדים משם, omdim misham,
do not leave there, do not, you know, end the day עד
שיכלו כל מעות שבשופר, ad sheyichlu kol maos shebashofar, until they see
that all the money in the שופר, shofar, that was what they
called the box, because if you think about how a שופר shofar
is configured, it's got a small hole on the top and a
big base on the bottom. So you can put the money in,
but you can't stick your hand in to get some money out,
I guess unless you unscrew the bottom, like in those צדקה tzedakah
boxes, like a piggy bank. Anyway, so בית דין beis din makes
sure that all the money gets used up. So again, it's because
there's a special supervising body that makes sure it gets done. But
as a general rule, you can't assume that things are going to
get done just because you asked somebody to do it for you.
So אמר, Amar, so that's his answer. אמר רב ששת מנא מנא
לן, Amar Rav Sheshet mina minalah, okay,
so רב ששת Rav Sheshet is going to try again to prove
you can assume that a שליח shaliach does what he's been authorized,
what he's been tasked to do I should say. דתניא, D'tanya, we
taught in the ברייתא, Braisa, האומר לחבירו צא ולקח. ha'omer l'chavero tzei
u'lekach.
You say to your friend, you know, go ahead and you can
pick some
figs from my fig tree and you can keep them for yourself,
it's a gift or I sold them to you, whatever. Go pick
them. Okay, now of course, as soon as you pick those figs
from the fig tree, there's going to be a problem that they're
טבל. tevel. They don't have תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot taken from it.
So can we assume, here's the question, that the בעל הבית ba'al
ha-bayit since he told me to pick is going to be take
care of it and make sure that he takes תרומות ומעשרות terumot
u-ma'asrot from stuff he has in his house that will, you know,
exempt my the figs? The only problem is he doesn't know how
many figs I'm picking and therefore, even if he wanted to, he
couldn't because תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot is a what מעשר ma'aser is
a very specific amount so you have to know the quantity. So
here's the הלכה: halacha: he tells me to go pick figs and
for myself, אוכל מהן עראי, ochel me-hen arai, I can eat from
them
in an עראי arai like a sort of an ad hoc basis
like not sitting down and being קובע, koveia, establishing a meal. You're
allowed to eat from them עראי arai until a certain stage, until
that they've been sort of processed and so on. So even though
they're טבל, tevel, you're allowed to eat עראי. ומעשרן ודאי, arai u-me'asran
vadai but if I want to eat them in a קבוע kavu'a
like sit down and have a meal with them then I definitely
have to take תרומות ומעשרות, terumot u-ma'asrot, there's no question the owner
did not do it because he didn't know how many I picked.
Now if he says to me, מלא לך כל כלי זה תאנים
מתאנתי, malei lecha kol keli zeh te'einim mite'einati, he gives me a
very specific amount, fill up this basket with figs and you can
have the basket, so we know exactly what the amount is. So
therefore if he wanted to he could have taken תרומות ומעשרות. terumot
u-ma'asrot. So what do we say? אוכל מהן עראי, ochel me-hen arai,
same הלכה, halacha, if I want to eat from them like ad
hoc I can, but let's say I want to eat קבוע, kavu'a,
I want to have a sort of fixed meal with them, so
מעשרן דמאי, me'asran demai, then I take תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot but
I do it as if it were דמאי demai because it's questionable.
Maybe the owner took תרומות ומעשרות, terumot u-ma'asrot, maybe he didn't. So
now if I want to eat from them in a non-ad hoc
basis I have to take תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot but not out
of a definite obligation, out of a דמאי. demai. What difference does
it make? As long as I'm taking תרומות ומעשרות? terumot u-ma'asrot? The
difference is like this: after I take the מעשר, ma'aser, I have
to take the מעשר ma'aser out of a doubt because if I
don't take it the grain is טבל. tevel. Now what do you
normally do with מעשר? ma'aser? Who do you give it to? לוי.
Levi. But after it's been taken, it leaves the realm of איסור,
issur, it's solved the grain from being טבל tevel and now as
a ספק איסור safek issur I had to do it, it might
have been טבל, tevel, but now it's a ספק safek of ownership.
The לוי Levi says it's my מעשר ma'aser and I say prove
it, maybe I wasn't obligated to take תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u-ma'asrot. So
I separate the מעשר ma'aser but I keep it for myself. Okay,
so that's what why it matters that we're calling it דמאי demai
rather than ודאי. vadai. You still have to do it but there's
a consequence of who gets to keep the grain after it's been
separated. Anyway so that's the הלכה halacha that I have to be
concerned that maybe it's possible the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayit did it
on himself on his own in that case, במה דברים אמורים, bameh
devarim amurim,
I'm sorry did I skip a line? עראי arai. ומעשרן ודאי u-me'asran
vadai, מלא לך... malei lecha... yeah I know. במה דברים אמורים, bameh
devarim amurim, when is this true that it's only a question whether
the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayit did it? בעם הארץ. be-am ha-aretz. If
the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayit is an עם הארץ, am ha-aretz, he's
a normal farmer and he's not somebody of this small group called
חבר chaver which are very scrupulous about תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u-ma'asrot. אבל
בחבר, aval be-chaver, if the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayit was a
חבר, chaver, אוכל ואינו צריך לעשר דברי רבי. ochel ve-eino tzarich le-aser
divrei Rabbi. Then I can definitely know that he took it. A
חבר chaver would not tell me to go take figs and not
make sure that he had taken care of it himself. So if
he told me to go take figs and he knew how much
he had told me to take a basket worth, I can be
confident that he took תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot in his house for
me because he wouldn't give me food that was problematic. That's the
assumption I can make. That's what רבי Rabbi says. ורבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר, ve-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel who was רבי's Rabbi father says, במה דברים
אמורים בעם הארץ. Bamedvar amurim b'am ha'aretz. When is this true that
it's a ספק safek if the owner took תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot
for me? By an עם הארץ. am ha-aretz. אבל בחבר, aval be-chaver,
if the owner was a חבר, chaver, אינו אוכל עד שיעשר, eino
ochel ad she-ye'aser, then you ודאי vadai have to take מעשר, ma'aser,
the exact opposite of רבי. Rabbi. רבי Rabbi said if the owner
was a חבר chaver I can assume he did it for me.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel said if the owner
was a חבר chaver I can be certain he didn't do it
for me. Why? לפי שלא נחשדו חברים לתרום שלא מן המוקף, lefi
she-lo nechshedu chaverim litrom she-lo min ha-mukaf, because a חבר chaver on
the one hand רבי Rabbi is saying the חבר chaver is so
scrupulous he'll protect me from sin, but רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel spoke speaks about being scrupulous about his own observance.
And therefore you're not supposed to take תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot unless
all of the stuff is together. So here he won't take for
me תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot on the stuff at home because it's
not together with the stuff in my basket. So this of course
becomes this interesting question which the גמרא's Gemara actually going to directly
get to which is, you know, do I am I willing to
compromise a little bit on some detail for my own observance for
the sake of somebody else's spiritual well-being? Okay, but that's the debate
of רבי Rabbi and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel.
רבי Rabbi said the חבר's chaver going to be sure I'm taken
care of. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says the
חבר's chaver going to be sure he's taken care of in terms
of religiously and therefore he won't separate תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot on
The dates, the figs that I have that are not together with
his figs.
So we don't take the approach like that, you see that the
חבר chaver would assume that the person who picked the figs would
take מעשר maaser on that portion that he picked.
Right, and so it depends is the person picking the figs a
חבר chaver or an עם הארץ am ha'aretz also, but right, you
know, that but right there's always this question of what assumptions are
you making about the other person. Right. So presumably the person picking
is a חבר chaver because if the משנה mishna is telling you
what to do, so it's only talking to the חבר, chaver, it's
not talking to the עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, you know. It's assuming
the guy, and the גמרא Gemara will say that alright well the
גמרא Gemara will say that anyway in a minute for another reason.
But even if it's an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, right, you'd still
assume that he did, because he has to do something, right? Right,
that's
true,
that's true.
Anyway, but you are correct. Part of the question also has to
be what assumption is the חבר chaver making about what I'm doing
is also relevant to this whole thing. So this is the debate
of רבי Rebbi and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel.
So now אמר רבי, amar Rebbi, says רבי, Rebbi, נראים דברי מדברי
אבא, nirim devarai midivrei Abba, my I actually prefer my opinion to
my father's. I would assume so or else he wouldn't have disagreed
with him, but anyway now he's basically going to defend his
position. Why? מוטב שיחשדו חברים לתרום שלא מן המוקף, mutav sheyechashdu chaverim
litrum shelo min hamukaf, I think it would be better that a
חבר chaver would be suspect, and suspect here doesn't just mean suspect,
it's better for a חבר chaver to take from stuff that's not
all together and violate that sort of small detail about how you're
ideally supposed to take תרומות ומעשרות, terumos umaasros, ולא יאכילו לעמי הארץ
טבלים, velo yachilu le-amei ha'aretz tevalim, and rather than the other side
of the equation which is because of your inaction or in-action somebody
is eating טבל. tevel. So I actually think the פרומער frummer thing
to do and the thing I can assume a חבר chaver will
do and that he will take תרומות ומעשרות. terumos umaasros. By the
way I have to tell you before we get on it's very
interesting because you know in terms of הלכות כיבוד אב ואם, hilchos
kibbud av va'em, right you're not supposed to contradict what your father
said. So here now you can obviously have a הלכתי halachic argument
with them, you know, debate, obviously because in the גמרא Gemara very
often you had, you know, sons arguing with their fathers הלכתית. halachically.
But what is interesting is like נראים דברי מדברי אבא, nirim devarai
midivrei Abba, the very sort of you know direct way of sort
of saying rather than just defending your position, you know, it raises
interesting questions about that also, you know, he actually puts his his
his opinion before his father's opinion.
Right, because first you had רבי's Rebbi opinion in the ברייתא braisa
and then you had רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel.
So anyway interesting I just I raise that as a question in
terms of הלכות כיבוד אב ואם. hilchos kibbud av va'em. But let's
see where the גמרא Gemara goes. עד כאן ad kan says the
גמרא. Gemara. So what do we see? לא פליגי, lo peligi, the
only thing they're arguing about is אלא דמר סבר נחשדו ומר סבר
לא נחשדו. ela demar savar nechashdu umar savar lo nechashdu. One says
they're suspect, meaning we can assume they took when it wasn't all
together, and the other says they're not suspect of doing that. אבל,
aval, putting that issue aside, כולי עלמא חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו. kulei
alma chazaka shaliach oseh shelichuso. Everybody are still willing to assume that
were it not for the concern of taking stuff that isn't all
together, we can assume that a שליח shaliach did his שליחות, shelichus,
that the בעל הבית baal habayis took תרומות ומעשרות. terumos umaasros. Now
that is a very weak argument by analogy because it's an argument
by analogy because why is that not so relevant? Here we can
assume the בעל הבית baal habayis took תרומות ומעשרות terumos umaasros so
you see שליח עושה שליחותו. shaliach oseh shelichuso.
Whose שליח shaliach is he, right? I mean even though before we
spoke about כהנים Kohanim there's an implicit sense כהנים Kohanim have a
responsibility to bring for you, you know, for your קרבנות. korbanos. Here
what type of a שליחות shelichus is it? So you know רש"י
Rashi says that basically since they have a responsibility to do it
to make sure that they don't cause the other guy to sin,
that's similar to a responsibility that I agree to do something for
you. But of course that's a pretty weak analogy, right? I mean
I might take one responsibility much more seriously than the other. You
could argue both ways. If we directly as a personal interaction I
committed to do something to you maybe I'll take that more seriously.
Or the other, if it's if I have to protect myself, you
from sinning and me from causing you to sin, I'm going to
do something much more sort of, you know, take it much more
seriously. But anyway that's the analogy the גמרא Gemara makes. It might
be relevant because in all of these cases and I'll get back
to this point in a minute, if the שליח shaliach doesn't do
his שליחות, shelichus, the other person will sin. If I didn't put
out the תחומין techumin you'll violate הלכות תחומין. hilchos techumin. If I
didn't bring the קרבן korban at the right time you'll violate כרת,
kares, you know, so so there is an aspect here of me
doing the שליחות shelichus is also ensuring protecting you there's a greater
sort of urgency for me to do it or responsibility because it's
preventing you from sinning. So this is the גמרא's Gemara argument.
Okay. So you see that normally that you could assume that I'll
take care of it. סבר רב נחמן, Savar Rav Nachman, and that's
דאורייתא. de-oraisa. Now by the way תוספות Tosafos says it's not really
דאורייתא de-oraisa because תרומה teruma and מעשר maaser on fruit is not
דאורייתא. de-oraisa. It's basically on דגן תירוש ויצהר dagan tirosh ve-yitzhar like
grain and you know and olives and grapes or whatever oil and
oil and wine. But nevertheless it's seen as a דאורייתא de-oraisa because
it's part of the תרומות ומעשרות terumos umaasros category which is a
דאורייתא. de-oraisa. שפיר Shapir says that's an argument that it works. סבר
רב ששת Savar Rav Sheshes says that's an argument that it works.
So Rav Nachman even as Similar to the point before but very
more specific because a חבר chaver is so scrupulous about laws of
תרומות Trumos and מעשרות, Maisros, he we can be certain that he
will not let allow food that he is distributing that is somehow
leaving his control to not be taken care of. So this is
a special area we know the חבר chaver will be on top
of. And in general case that I should act to make sure
you don't violate תחומין, tchumin, who knows? I'll be lazy about it.
But if I'm a חבר chaver and it's about תרומות Trumos and
מעשרות, Maisros, there everybody agrees that I take a heightened responsibility to
make sure that some that I do not let you have access
to food that has not been taken care of. Okay, so that's
a special case. Yes. Was חבר chaver like an official status? Yes.
Yes, there was an official status and there's actually discussions about how
does somebody get into becoming a חבר, chaver, when would somebody get
kicked out? It was really this like very clear sort of, you
know, group, like a club, you know, about people that were scrupulous
about eating about תרומות Trumos and מעשרות. Maisros. You know, you understand
why in the, you know, in the, you know, in the Gospels
you have all this thing about Jesus eating with all these people,
you know, and the tax collectors and the prostitutes and, you know,
because the groups you ate with were very much about a hierarchy
and, you know, created senses of lines and, you know, and social
like distinctions. So yes, חבר chaver was a very well-defined group in
terms of these issues of תרומות Trumos and מעשרות. Maisros. Okay. What?
השגחה? Hashgacha? Yeah, but it was more like people that could trust
one another, you know, in terms of this. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay, so let's keep on going. אמר מר,
Amar Mar, now let's now we're going to go back. We haven't
proven one way or the other way about Rav Nachman and Rav
Sheshes, but now we have to wrap up this discussion about the
חבר chaver will he assume he took תרומות Trumos and מעשרות Maisros
or not. במה דברים אמורים bameh devarim amurim בעם הארץ. be-am ha-aretz.
When is it a question whether it was taken for you if
the owner was an עם הארץ? am ha'aretz? אבל בחבר, Aval b'chaver,
if the owner was a חבר, chaver, אוכל ואינו צריך לעשר דברי
רבי. ochel v'eino tzarich l'aseir divrei Rebbe. Rebbe says you can assume
definitely he took it for me, he wouldn't want me to sin
about this. So the גמרא Gemara says האי עם הארץ דקאמר ליה
למאן. hai ham ha'aretz d'kamar lei l'man. So when we said the
first case was when the owner was an עם הארץ am ha'aretz
and then you take דמאי, dmai, who's he saying it to? Who
is the guy collecting the figs? אילימא דקאמר לעם הארץ חבריה, Ileima
d'kamar l'am ha'aretz chaveirei, if he's saying to a fellow עם הארץ,
am ha'aretz, so first of all I assume as I said before
to Dov, although it's debatable, that the משניות Mishnas are only talking
to חברים. chaveirim. The משניות Mishnas are talking, you know, assume that
the person paying attention to all the rules is a חבר, chaver,
but Dov's right, an עם הארץ am ha'aretz maybe does, maybe doesn't.
But it says it can't be that in the first case it
was an עם הארץ am ha'aretz telling an עם הארץ am ha'aretz
to go collect. Why? דמאי מציית? Dmai mitzayes? He's not going to
take something דמאי, dmai, he's not going to suspect his friend עם
הארץ. am ha'aretz. Meaning when we say if the עם הארץ am
ha'aretz tells you to collect the figs you have to suspect maybe
he didn't take care of it and you have to take yourself,
so if you are also an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, you're not
going to suspect him because you assume that, you know, everybody is
responsible. You don't have the same sort of suspicious look on עמי
הארץ amei ha'aretz that חז"ל Chazal do. So you won't listen to
us if we tell you to take דמאי. dmai. אלא, Ella, so
you have to assume בעם הארץ דקאמר ליה לחבר. b'am ha'aretz d'kamar
lei l'chaver. The עם הארץ am ha'aretz was talking to a חבר.
chaver. As I said, I assume the person the משניות Mishnayos are
talking about or the ברייתות Baraysos are talking about is a חבר.
chaver. Okay, so the first case was an עם הארץ am ha'aretz
told a חבר, chaver, so the חבר chaver has to take דמאי
dmai because maybe the עם הארץ am ha'aretz didn't take care of
it. And then the second case is the חבר chaver told you
to take. So אימא סיפא, ima seifa, so let's look now at
the second case. נראין דברי מדברי אבא, Nirin divrei midvrai mi'divrei Abba,
says Rebbe, my opinion seems more correct than my father's. מוטב שיחשדו
חברים לתרום שלא
מן המוקף,
Mutav she'yachshdu
chaveirim litrom she'lo min hamukaf, I'd rather assume
that the חבר, chaver, the owner, took when it wasn't all together,
ואל יאכילו עמי הארץ טבלים, v'al yachilu amei ha'aretz tevelin, and he
won't be and he won't lead to the possibility that an עם
הארץ am ha'aretz will eat טבל. tevel. So the גמרא Gemara says
עמי הארץ מאי בעיא התם? amei ha'aretz mai baya hasam? What's an
עם הארץ am ha'aretz doing there? We just said that the guy
collecting the figs was a חבר. chaver. And this goes to Dov's
point. If a חבר chaver tells a חבר chaver to collect the
figs, maybe the owner can assume the guy collecting will be responsible
on his own and I don't have to take care of him.
So it says you see in the second case the reason we're
assuming the owner is assuming the responsibility is because the guy who's
collecting is an עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. So what's the case? Is
the collector a חבר chaver or is the collector an עם הארץ?
am ha'aretz? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, רישא
בעם הארץ דקאמר ליה לחבר. reisha b'am ha'aretz d'kamar lei l'chaver. You
were right, the beginning is the עם הארץ am ha'aretz told a
חבר. chaver. How about the end case, which is if a חבר's
chaver telling a חבר chaver then it's not a problem of causing
the עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz to sin? So סיפא בחבר שאמר לעם
הארץ בחבר אחר שומעו. seifa b'chaver she'amar l'am ha'aretz b'chaver acher shome'o.
So he creates a very sort of, you know, complicated case. You
told the עם הארץ am ha'aretz to collect, so you therefore if
you're a חבר chaver you're going to take care of it because
you can't trust the עם הארץ am ha'aretz to take care of
it. But then a חבר chaver overheard or a חבר chaver now
wants to eat from the figs that the עם הארץ am ha'aretz
collected. So therefore, in both cases, we're talking about what will the
חבר chaver do, but nevertheless, in the second case, the concern is
that since you gave your directions to an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz,
you will take care to make sure that everything is taken care
of. Okay, so that's a little complicated how we do that, but
the basic point is, we're assuming on the one hand the חבר
chaver is the one who is listening to our directions, but number
two, what's the case where we assume the חבר chaver took care
of things? He didn't want him to sin was when he was
speaking to an עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. And this goes back to
Dov's point, if the חבר chaver is speaking to a חבר, chaver,
maybe the owner won't take care of it; he'll assume that since
the other guy's the חבר, chaver, he'll take care of it. So
how you act is always a little bit of an assumption of
how you think the other guy is going to act. Okay, now
we get on to the debate of רבי Rebbi and his father.
רבי סבר, Rebbi savar, top of ל"ב עמוד ב', Lamed Beis Amud
Beis, רבי's Rebbi of the opinion. Isn't that the case you mentioned
where he separated it or where truma was really on it? Right,
so that's the second case, the חבר chaver and the חבר. chaver.
It doesn't ever tell you what the case is of חבר chaver
and חבר. chaver. That would be the latter, פשט pshat is that
it would be a ספק safek most probably, unless you could make
the assumption the exact opposite, which is right, but that's a likely
consequence. Okay, so now what's the debate? רבי סבר אותו חבר אוכל
ואינו צריך לעשר, Rebbi savar oto chaver ochel ve'eino tzarich le'aser, that
if a חבר chaver told an עם הארץ am ha'aretz and then
another חבר chaver wants to eat the food of the עם הארץ,
am ha'aretz, so he says that you don't have to worry about
taking מעשר, ma'aser, the guy who's eating from the food of the
collector. דודאי עשר אוהו חבר קמא, devaday iser ohu chaver kama, the
first חבר, chaver, the owner, definitely took care of it. Why? אילוי,
iloi, because he definitely gave directions to an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz,
he was going to take care to make sure that this עם
הארץ am ha'aretz wouldn't eat טבל. tevel. And therefore you can assume
the owner took care of it. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר לא
יאכל עד שיעשר. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer lo yochal ad sheye'aser.
No, the opposite, you have to definitely take מעשר, ma'aser, not only
דמאי, demai, the owner did not do anything. לפי שלא נחשדו חברים
לתרום שלא מן המוקף, lefi shelo nechshdu chaverim litrom shelo min hamukaf,
because he's going to be so scrupulous about his own sort of
religiosity that he's not going to take with stuff that's not all
together, even if somebody else might sin as a result. ואמר ליה
רבי, ve'amar lei Rebbi, so רבי Rebbi said back to him, מוטב
שיחשדו חברים לתרום שלא מן המוקף ואל יאכילו עמי הארץ טבלים, mutav
sheyechasdu chaverim litrom shelo min hamukaf ve'al ya'achilu amei ha'aretz tevalim, I'd
rather חברים chaverim be suspect of violating this rule of taking stuff
that's not all together and not lead to עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz
eating טבלים. tevalim. By the way, it's a fascinating question, because on
the one hand, they seem to be arguing policy. What should you
do in that case? Should you violate this small prohibition and save
somebody else from sin, or should you be careful about even the
smallest sort of thing for your own observance? But on the other
hand, while they seem to be arguing policy, but what the real
question though is not a policy question, but it's a practical issue.
למעשה, lema'aseh, how do people act? What do חברים chaverim do? Are
they more concerned with somebody else's big sin or are they more
concerned with their small sin? So is it a big sin or
just not advisable? Well, and even then, it's not even really a
sin, exactly, it's even not advisable. But okay, but that's the point.
Meaning, on the one hand, it seems like they're arguing what should
a חבר chaver do, but in order to question how you deal
with this particular case, the real issue is what can we assume
this person actually did do? But okay, let's see where the גמרא
Gemara goes with this. במאי קמיפלגי? bemai kamiflagi? What is this really,
what's at the root of this debate? רבי סבר ניחא ליה לחבר
דליעביד הוא איסורא קלילא ולא ליעביד עם הארץ איסורא רבה. Rebbi savar
nicha lei lechaver deli'avid hu issura kalila velo liya'avid am ha'aretz issura
rabba. Now again, notice it doesn't state this as an absolute; it
speaks about, it does say as a policy issue it frames it
more in terms of how will people act. רבי Rebbi says a
חבר chaver would rather, meaning not saying what I'm saying you should
do, but this is the reality, a חבר chaver would rather do
a little prohibition—and it's not even really a prohibition, it's just like
not advisable—rather than somebody else on his account do a big איסור.
issur. ורבי שמעון בן גמליאל סבר ניחא ליה לחבר דליעביד עם הארץ
איסורא רבה ואיהו אפילו איסורא קלילא לא ליעביד. veRebbi Shimon ben Gamliel
savar nicha lei lechaver deli'avid am ha'aretz issura rabba ve'ihu afilu issura
kalila lo liya'avid. No, a חבר chaver would rather let an עם
הארץ am ha'aretz do a big איסור, issur, I'm going to keep
my hands totally clean. Sadly, we do know that that is how
a lot of religious people act. I don't care about anybody else,
I have to be completely clean and not get my hands dirty
at all. So this actually turns into a question, although they're not
actually telling you הלכתית halachically what you should do, they're trying to
guess what the חבר chaver did do, this actually gets into this
issue about whether we say אומרים לאדם חטא כדי שיזכה חברך. omerim
le'adam chatei kedei sheyizkeh chavercha. Do we tell one person to sin
a smaller sin to protect somebody from a larger sin? So this
was an issue at the beginning of מסכת שבת, Masechet Shabbat, and
תוספות Tosafos sort of says sometimes we say yes, sometimes we say
no, and he gives a couple of interesting distinctions why, when we
would say it. The first big distinction is: in this case, you're
to blame. You basically told the guy to collect, it's your responsibility,
and therefore if it's your responsibility, yeah, you gotta get your hands
a little dirty to save that guy from a sin. It's not
just some random person sinning, it's actually as a result of you.
So you've got a responsibility to address it. And then he says
the opposite would be true in the opposite direction. Let's say the
other person is sinning. due to that person's own negligence. Okay, meaning
there's a middle case, right? It's not your responsibility and that person
doesn't know better. Okay, nobody is to blame, do you do something
small to save somebody from something big? But then we have the
case where you're to blame, you got to do it, and the
other case where he's to blame and he was really negligent or
did something wrong and that maybe more frees you from responsibility. So
תוספות Tosafot sees, yeah, so תוספות Tosafot sees that there's two extremes.
When that other person is really to blame, then you don't have
to, you know, take responsibility. Wait, that's a good question. Should it,
maybe you're right, should it. I mean when you're when you have
a responsibility, you have to do a small violation to save person
from big. And the question is when nobody's to blame and how
much and how much does that sort of, you know, and that's
what's debated in the גמרא, Gemara, whether אומרים לאדם חטא כדי שיזכה
חברך. omrim l'adam chatei k'dei she'yizkeh chaveirecha. I have to see. Yes.
He's to blame but because of ignorance, that's also a really... Right,
so that also gets to the question about what do you consider
to be to blame and what's פשיעה. pshia. תוספות Tosafot is dealing
with the case in the beginning of שבת Shabbis where the guy
puts a bread in the oven, you know, like on שבת. Shabbis.
And the question is are you going to take it out of
the oven to save him from doing... so there you violated שבת.
Shabbis. And now I should do a violation because you just you
did a violation? So anyway, that's interesting. I also so that's in
terms of that issue of אומרים לאדם חטא. omrim l'adam chatei. I
also want to say something about חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו. chazaka shaliach
oseh shelichuto. There's also the question about how do we פוסקין paskin
about that. Do we assume חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו chazaka shaliach oseh
shelichuto by דאורייתא d'oraisa or not? So it's debated by רב נחמן
Rav Nachman and רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. So it's debated by the
גאונים. Geonim. And the גאונים Geonim actually ruled that we rule like
רב נחמן Rav Nachman that it... that we don't say it by
דאורייתא. d'oraisa. But רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam and a number of ראשונים
Rishonim rule like... I'm sorry, let me just... No, I said it
wrong. They say we rule like רב ששת Rav Sheshet that we
do say it by דאורייתא. d'oraisa. But then תוספות Tosafot brings, you
know, some בעלי התוספות Ba'alei HaTosafot that say actually we don't say
it. So it's a מחלוקת גאונים ראשונים machloket Geonim Rishonim how we
פוסקין paskin about that as well. And here too, תוספות Tosafot says
there might be cases that everybody agrees on. Like the cases in
the גמרא Gemara where you are if you don't do what you
were asked to do, somebody is going to sin as a result.
If I don't put down that עירוב eruv as you told me
to, I know you're assuming the עירוב eruv will be there and
you'll go outside the תחום. tchum. There we there might be more
reason to assume we do say חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו chazaka shaliach
oseh shelichuto even by דאורייתא. d'oraisa. Where it's not going to be
something that you'll sin as a result, there we might not be
able to make that same type of an assumption. So there's a
question there as well how we פוסקין paskin and also the issue
about responsibility and sin ties into that as well. I do want
to say one last thing about the חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו, chazaka
shaliach oseh shelichuto, which is by analogy and it's a very important
תשובה tshuva of רב משה פיינשטיין. Rav Moshe Feinstein. רב משה Rav
Moshe was asked about cases about people in Russia, you know, obviously
this was before, you know, the opening of the doors of the
Soviet Union. That you know you had like parents that were observant,
you know, elderly parents and their children were non-observant and they wanted
to know like can they eat in their children's home if their
children promise to, you know, make sure that everything is כשר. kosher.
And רב משה Rav Moshe says, you know, from a technical standpoint,
the child doesn't have נאמנות ne'emanus because even though we say עד
אחד נאמן באיסורין, eid echad ne'eman b'issurin, if the person themselves doesn't
keep כשר, kosher, doesn't keep שבת Shabbis and so on, you can't
trust them. רב משה Rav Moshe says that idea of נאמנות ne'emanus
is only as a formal rule assuming that you, you know, don't
yourself really know what's going on. He says but if you have
complete trust in this person, then and you know that this person
they say they're going to do this that they're going to do
it. So you don't have to go by these formal rules of
נאמנות. ne'emanus. You actually have a real knowledge that, you know, that
a certainty that it was taken care of because of your knowledge
of this person. Now, that's interesting because he a little bit backpedaled
because he was asked a similar question later about another case, I
think about like a השגחה hashgacha case or something else, which wasn't
so much of a שעת הדחק sha'at hadachak and it wasn't a
father and his daughter, you know, it was some other person. And
this is a real question by השגחות. hashgachos. Like let's say, you
know, sometimes it's, you know, the non-Jews are better at keeping to
the rules than the פרום frum Jews who they think they know
better or whatever whatever the case might be. And it's a real
question by השגחה hashgacha whether you go by formal standards or do
you go by your real knowledge of the people that are involved.
So it's interesting in thinking about חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו. chazaka shaliach
oseh shelichuto. Like I can tell you I know people that I
could say ודאי אין שליח עושה שליחותו. vadai ein shaliach oseh shelichuto.
And then I know other people who I could say there's no
question, right? חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו. chazaka shaliach oseh shelichuto. So how
much do those factor in to like a formal rule of חזקה
שליח עושה שליחותו? chazaka shaliach oseh shelichuto? So that's interesting and רב
משה Rav Moshe definitely feels in some cases you go by, you
know, what you really know to be the case or can really
assume to be the case regardless of what... what? Follow the formal
rule but you're not so sure. Like עד אחד נאמן באיסורין. eid
echad ne'eman b'issurin. Right, so that would be right, the same type
of thing. I mean there's a lot of rules about somebody becoming
נחשד nechshad and so on, but let's say you don't have a
particular reason, you know, but you just know this guy's a little,
right? So I would say that that is an interesting question. of
can you still follow the Halachic rule and be like, you know,
Halachically like so to speak, you know, like exonerated because of oh,
I was following the Halachic. Yeah, I'd have to see I'd have
to see if there's a parallel discussion in the opposite direction. I
mean right once you start once you start deconstructing the formal rules,
right, what good are the formal rules? Right. And then you get
things like we sometimes rely on the 24 hour rule for כלים.
Kelim. Right, I think that that's a good question. That idea of
the 24 hour rule for כלים Kelim for example, one of the
things it's based on is you don't use a כלי Kli within
24 hours mostly, but if you're dealing with like a restaurant, they
actually say you can't rely on that because the כלים Kelim are
used on a very very regular basis. So it does raise, you're
right, a very good question of the relationship of a חזקה Chazakah
with a certain amount of knowledge of facts on the ground. And
not like a and not a clear knowledge against it, but you
know, certain reasons to suspect and how much the חזקה, Chazakah, obviously
the חזקה Chazakah has to play a function or else what would
be the point of it. Okay, so let's take a look now
as we continue to the next משנה. Mishnah. Just get a little
bit started with that. נתנו באילן למעלה מעשרה טפחים, Natanu be'ilan lemala
me'asara tefachim, you put it, now we're talking about where it's placed.
If it's in a tree higher than ten טפחים, tefachim, אין עירובו
עירוב, ein eruvo eruv, it doesn't count. למטה מעשרה טפחים, lemata me'asara
tefachim, lower than ten טפחים, tefachim, עירובו עירוב, eruvo eruv, it does.
So it's not clear what this is about, the גמרא Gemara will
unpack this. נתנו בבור, Natanu be'vor, if you put it in a
well, אפילו עמוק מאה אמה, afilu amok me'ah ama, even if it's
a hundred אמות amot deep, עירובו עירוב, eruvo eruv, it's good. Why
shouldn't it be? It's in a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, it's fine.
The question is what's the problem with the tree? Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. יתיב רבי חייא בר אבא ורבי אסי
ורבא בר נתן ויתיב רב נחמן גבייהו. Yasiv Rabbi Chiya bar Abba
ve'Rabbi Assi ve'Rava bar Nasan ve'yasiv Rav Nachman gavayhu. רבי חייא בר
אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba and רבי אסי Rabbi Assi and רבא
בר נתן Rava bar Nasan were sitting and רב נחמן Rav Nachman
was sitting by them. ויתיבי ואמרי Ve'yasiv ve'amri and these three Rabbis
were saying, האי אילן דקאי היכא, Hai ilan de'ka heicha, where's this
tree standing? This tree in the משנה? Mishnah? אילימא דקאי ברשות היחיד,
Ilei'ma de'ka bi'reshus hayachid, if it's in a private domain, a רשות
היחיד, reshus hayachid, you've got this tree surrounded by a fence and
the עירוב eruv is up in the tree, מה לי למעלה מה
לי למטה, mah li lemala mah li lemata, what do I care
how high or low the עירוב eruv is? רשות היחיד עולה עד
לרקיע, Reshus hayachid oleh ad larakia, you know, it's all a רשות
היחיד, reshus hayachid, the area around the tree, who cares if it's
higher up in the tree? That's necessity of using שמשה. shemisha. Okay,
but that's true even if it's lower down, the גמרא Gemara will
get to that, so hold on. אלא דקאי ברשות הרבים, Ella de'ka
bi'reshus harabim, it must be that the tree is in the middle
of the רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Okay, and therefore the problem is
if you take the עירוב eruv out of the tree and you're
standing in a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, you're carrying from רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid to רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. So even if you're not
going to actually take the עירוב, eruv, you have to, like we
saw before about the כהן Kohen in the cemetery, be able to
have access to it. Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara is
going to now say. דמסתוין לשבות היכא, De'mistavein lishpos heicha, where are
you intending in your mind for, you know, your place that שבת
Shabbos will begin? אילימא דמסתוין לשבות למעלה, Ilei'ma de'nistavein lishpos lemala, if
you say oh, I'm starting שבת Shabbos up in the tree with
my עירוב, eruv, okay, so הוא ועירובו במקום אחד, hu ve'eruvo bi'makom
echad, so what's the big deal? The tree is רשות היחיד, reshus
hayachid, you're in a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, fine, what should be
the problem? Now Michael says a problem, you can't climb on trees,
we'll get to that. But אלא, ella, but that won't be an
issue. אלא דמסתוין לשבות למטה, Ella nistavein lishpos lemata, here's what's going
on in the משנה. Mishnah. You were thinking in your mind I'm
starting שבת Shabbos at the base of the tree, but your עירוב
eruv was up in the tree. So now where you're starting שבת,
Shabbos, you don't have access to your עירוב. eruv. You have to
be able to have access to your עירוב eruv from the place
you designated as where you're starting שבת. Shabbos. And the reason you
don't have access, sure you can reach up and touch it, but
you can't actually get it and use it because you'd be taking
from רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. And
now the גמרא Gemara asks Michael's question. Who cares if it's high
or low, you can't get it out of the tree anyway? והא
קמשתמש באילן, Ve'ha kamishtamesh be'ilan, you're using the tree. So you're not
allowed to get it out of the tree wherever it is, so
why is it okay even if it's lower? So the גמרא Gemara
says look, we were right about our position. לעולם דקאי ברשות הרבים,
Le'olam de'ka bi'reshus harabim, the tree is in a רשות הרבים, reshus
harabim, דמסתוין לשבות למטה, ve'nistavein lishpos lemata, and you planned on starting
שבת Shabbos at the base of the tree. And why do you
have access to it because if it's under ten טפחים, tefachim, it's
not in a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, it's like maybe a כרמלית
karmelis or something. ורבי היא, Ve'Rabbi hi, now how about the problem
about taking something off of the tree? Why is that allowed? Because
this is רבי, Rabbi, דאמר כל דבר שהוא משום שבות לא גזרו
עליו בין השמשות. de'amar kol davar shehu mishum shevus lo gazru lei
bein hashmashos. We've seen this before, רבי Rabbi says דרבנן d'rabanans don't
apply in בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. And this becomes a very important
principle for הלכות עירוב hilchos eruv because עירוב eruv is defined by
the בין השמשות, bein hashmashos, that determines when it takes effect. And
the question, do you have access to it or not? What about
if you had to violate דרבנן? d'rabanans? Right, and we had that
before about well in theory I could reverse my נזירות nezirus or
I could be reverse the תרומה ומעשר. trumah u'ma'aser. And if you
could do those things during בין השמשות, bein hashmashos, it's considered like
the עירוב eruv works. So here, even if it's שבת Shabbat now.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, but as long as it was working בין השמשות,
bein hashma'shos, that's when it defines it. So even though it's in
the tree, as long as it's if it's in a רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid high up, that's a biblical prohibition. There's no way I
could bring it down to me at the base of the tree.
But if it's lower down, even though I would have to violate
a rabbinic prohibition of using the tree, since it would take effect
בין השמשות, bein hashma'shos, that's considered to be within my access. And
that's how the משנה mishnah makes sense. Don't worry about using the
tree, only worry about the biblical issue of רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
Let's just sort of see this one more time. אמר להו רב
נחמן, Amar lehu Rav Nachman, so these were what these three rabbis
were saying. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman said to them, אישר, Iyasher,
יישר כח, yasher koach, that's a good explanation. וכן אמר שמואל, V'chein
amar Shmuel, and that's also how שמואל Shmuel explains this משנה.
mishnah. אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they said back
to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, פשריתה לכולי האי, Pashriteh l'kulei hai, you
went to such an effort to explain the משנה? mishnah? So the
גמרא Gemara says, what do you mean? אינהו נמי הכי קא פשרי
בה. Inhu nami hachi ka pashrei bah. That's also they also explained
the משנה mishnah that way. ורב נחמן Rav Nachman also agrees with
them, they've got a problem. אלא הכי אמרו ליה, Ella hachi amru
lei, this is what they said to רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. קבעיתוה
בגמרא, Kva'ituha b'Gemara, interestingly, have you taken this explanation of the משנה
mishnah and made it a standard part of your teaching? Meaning, you
know, it's one thing that we're discussing hypothetically, trying to figure out
a משנה. mishnah. It's another thing that we said, oh, here's פשט
pshat in the משנה, mishnah, and this is what we're regularly going
to teach when we learn this משנה mishnah about how we understand
what the משנה mishnah is talking about. So that's what they asked
רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. Have you made it like a fixed part
of your teaching? אמר להו אין, Amar lehu in, yes, this is
the standard way we explain this משנה. mishnah. איתמר נמי, Itmar nami,
and it was similarly taught, אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל, Amar Rav
Nachman amar Shmuel, הכא באילן העומד ברשות הרבים עסקינן. hacha b'ilan ha'omed
b'reshus harabbim askinan. רב נחמן Rav Nachman said this is what שמואל
Shmuel said. So here we see it became a גמרא, Gemara, it
became a מימרא, memra, it became a fixed rabbinic statement about this
משנה. mishnah. הכא באילן העומד ברשות הרבים עסקינן, Hacha b'ilan ha'omed b'reshus
harabbim askinan, if the tree is in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, גבוה
עשרה ורחב ארבעה, gavo'ah asarah v'rachav arba'ah, and it's ten high and
what we didn't say before, four by four טפחים tefachim wide. Why?
Because if it's not four by four טפחים tefachim wide, it's not
a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Okay, so it's four by four טפחים
tefachim wide and it's ten high, so it's in a רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid when it's at that height. ונתכוון לשבות למטה, V'niskapein lishbos
lemata, and you're intending to start שבת Shabbos at the base. ורבי
היא, V'Rabbi hi, and it's רבי, Rabbi, דאמר כל דבר שהוא משום
שבות לא גזרו עליו בין השמשות, d'amar kol davar shehu mishum shvus
lo gazru alav bein hashma'shos, that even though it's a rabbinic problem
of using the tree, and רש״י Rashi also throws in a כרמלית,
karmelis, even if it's lower than ten טפחים tefachim it's still a
כרמלית karmelis the tree, nevertheless, rabbinic issues don't matter. This is רבי.
Rabbi. And the explanation of the משנה mishnah is as we said,
the tree you're at the רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, that's where you're
starting, that's your base, and the עירוב eruv has to be accessible
and if it's in רשות היחיד reshus hayachid it's not. If it's
lower, it's accessible and therefore the עירוב eruv works.